Finding Aid for Evangeline Marie Lehman and Maurice Dumesnil papers, 1916-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Evangeline Marie Lehman and Maurice Dumesnil papers 1916-1974
Lehman, Evangeline Marie, 1896-1975.
861125 Aa 2; UAm
Papers of Evangeline Lehman, concert singer and composer, and of her husband Maurice Dumesnil, concert pianist and composer. Correspondence, press clippings and programs, and photographs relating to their professional careers.
1 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the University of Michigan School of Music Library (donor no. 5155 ) in 1984.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Evangeline Marie Lehman
Evangeline Marie Lehman, American composer and singer, born in Northville, Michigan, May 16, 1896; died in Highland Park, Michigan, February 28, 1975.
Lehman studied at the Oberlin Conservatory and then the Fontainbleau Conservatoire in France. In 1933, her oratorio St. Therese de l'Enfant Jesus won her a silver medal from the French ministry of Foreign Affairs. Many of her works such as her oratorio St. Therese, cantata La Nuit de Noel and her piano work Southland Frolic were performed in Paris, Uruguay, New York, San Francisco and Detroit. Lehman herself also appeared as a solo performer with major orchestras such as the Chicago Symphony, the Detroit Symphony, the Cleveland Symphony and leading orchestras in Europe.
Apart from being a composer and singer Lehman was a dedicated teacher. She had a studio of private students in Highland Park, Michigan, and gave numerous workshops at various institutions. She wrote a few articles, all published in Etude Magazine, on the technique and art of singing as well as on art song writing.
She was married to Maurice Dumesnil, a noted concert pianist. He was an ardent publicist of her music. He premiered many of her piano works and conducted the premier performance of the oratorio St. Therese. Dumesnil also translated many of her song texts into French.
Lehman was well known in the Detroit area and received an honorary Degree of Doctor of Music from the Detroit Institute of Musical Arts. In addition Lehman and Dumesnil made many concert appearances together both in the United States and Europe.
Maurice Dumesnil
Maurice Dumesnil, French pianist and conductor, born Angouleme, Charente, France, April 20, 1886; died Highland Park, Michigan, August 26, 1974.
Dumesnil studied at the Paris Conservatory under Isidor Philipp and Claude Debussy. Following his graduation in 1905 Dumesnil began a concert tour of Europe. During World War I he served as an officer in the French Field Artillery Corps. Immediately after his military service Dumesnil began concert tours of South America and served as an orchestral conductor in Mexico.
Dumesnil's first American tour was in 1927 at which time he brought Frederick Chopin's piano to the United States for a six month coast to coast tour. Because Dumesnil had been a student of Debussy he became known for his masterful interpretations of Debussy's piano works.
In 1931 Dumesnil married the American singer and composer Evangeline Lehman. However, because of Lehman's career plans the wedding was kept secret until 1942. At that time Dumesnil and Lehman had returned to the United States and Dumesnil wished to become an American citizen. He was told that his naturalization would be simplified if he were married to an American in the United States. So, Dumesnil and Lehman were married again in Kansas City and Dumesnil's application of United States citizenship was accepted.
In addition to Dumesnil's extensive teaching and touring he was well known as an interpreter of Debussy. Not only was his musical interpretation of Debussy's work considered valuable but he also published two volumes on Debussy. In 1933 he wrote How to Teach and Play Debussy and in 1940 he wrote Claude Debussy, Master of Dreams. Dumesnil also had a regular column in Etude Magazine.
Dumesnil enjoyed a wide and varied musical career and was well known and respected as both a performer and teacher.
The Lehman/Dumesnil collection is really two collections, but because of their marriage as well as their close professional association, their papers have been kept together. The collection has two series: Evangeline Lehman and Maurice Dumesnil. There are also three envelopes of photographs on both individuals. Included are portraits, candid snapshots, and photos of concert performances.
Subjects:
Lehman, Evangeline Marie, 1896-1975.; Music--United States.; Musicians--United States.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dumesnil, Maurice, 1886-1974.; Lehman, Evangeline Marie, 1896-1975.; Music--United States.; Musicians--United States.
Contributors:
Dumesnil, Maurice, 1886-1974.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Lehman, Evangeline
  The material on Evangeline Lehman is divided into the following subseries: Biographical includes passports, birth certificate, newspaper clippings and Lehman's parents marriage license. Writings includes a partially typed manuscript entitled: "Adolescent Singers and Suitable Materials For Their Voices," and reprints of journal articles written by Lehman. Musical Career includes materials (poster, programs, etc.) collected in connection with various performances of Lehman's oratorio St. Therese de 1'Enfant Jesus and programs and reviews of other Lehman performances. Correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence between Lehman and her friends and family. Awards contains information on Lehman's award of the silver medal from the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs in 1933 for the composition St. Therese de l'Enfant Jesus. Travel includes a travel diary, postcards sent to Lehman's parents and sister and a scrapbook from a 1954 trip to France.
  - Biographical
    - Biographical information (Box 1)
    - Passports and birth record (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Notebook of miscellaneous writings (Box 1)
    - Reprints of articles (Box 1)
  - Musical Career
    - Scrapbooks of St. Therese Oratorio, 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Poster from St. Therese Oratorio 1933 (Box 1)
    - Performance programs 1933-1962 (Box 1)
    - Reviews of Lehman's compositions (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing correspondence undated (Box 1)
    - Incoming correspondence 1952-1972 (Box 1)
  - Awards
    - Presentation of silver medal from French Ministry of Foreign Affairs August 2, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Travel
    - Travel diary 1954 from trip to France (Box 1)
    - Set of postcards to Lehman family 1954 (trip to France) (Box 1)
  - Journal (in French) (Box 1)
- Dumesnil, Maurice
  The material on Maurice Dumesnil is divided into the following subseries: Biographical includes newspaper clippings, passports, Dumesnil's naturalization papers and information regarding Dumesnil's brother, Gaston. Musical Career includes a scrapbook of the 1916-1919 tours of South and Central America and programs from many of Dumesnil's performances. Correspondence includes postcards written by Dumesnil from France in the 1950's and correspondence from Dumesnil's many friends, teachers and students.
  - Biographical
    - Newspaper clippings and personal materials (Box 1)
    - Passports and naturalization papers (Box 1)
    - Gaston Dumesnil miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Musical Career
    - Scrapbook of 1916-1919 tours of South and Central America (Box 1)
    - Programs of performances 1922-1941 (Box 1)
    - Programs of performances 1942-1956 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing (postcards) 1952-1953, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Incoming correspondence 1935-1955 (Box 1)
    - Incoming correspondence 1966-1974 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  Portraits, candid snapshots, photos of concert tours abroad, and photos of concert performances
  - Dumesnil alone (Box 1)
  - Lehman alone (Box 1)
  - Dumesnil/Lehman together; and photos of others (Box 1)
Related Material
The University of Michigan Music Library has a separate collection of the printed music, music manuscripts, sketchbooks and writings of Evangeline Lehman.